suppose you have a right triangle with
legs of length A and B and hypotenuse of
length C
you can draw squares off the legs
enclosing an area of a squared and of B
squared respectively
you can also draw a square off the
hypotenuse enclosing an area of c
squared let's see an interesting
dissection that'll give a formula for c
squared we can take these two lines off
the C by C square and shift them so that
they pass through the middle of the B by
b square notice we can shift the
original triangle so that it lies along
one of those lines and then we can
rotate the triangle about that line to
form a rectangle that covers part of the
B by b square
the two uncovered rectangles in the B by
b square have the same width by Symmetry
and this width can be computed then as
half the difference between the square
length and the leg length of the
triangle which is B minus a over two so
that the remaining side of the B by b
square has a length of B plus a over two
Again by symmetry this means we've cut
the B by b square into four congruent
trapezoids all with the same dimensions
we can shift these trapezoids as follows
over to the C by C Square
but notice there's a remaining Square
left on the inside the side length of
this Square can be computed as the
difference of B plus a over 2 and B
minus a over two but that's just a so we
can then shift the a by a square up and
now we've covered the entire C by C
Square therefore c squared must be equal
to B squared plus a squared
there is nothing special about the
particular right triangle that we chose
if a and b are the leg lengths of any
right triangle with hypotenuse C then a
squared plus b squared will always equal
c squared here we show a variety of
different right triangles morphing
through and each time we show the
dissection given by this proof it turns
out that the dissection of the B by B
squared and the a by a square will
always cover the C by C Square this is
the Pythagorean theorem As proved by
Henry dudenay